Hi, this is Matt Baker. Today I want to
show you seven different perspectives on
church history using this chart that was
made by a fan and posted on our useful
charts subreddit. It does a really good
job at demonstrating that there are two
very different ways to talk about
religion. There's the view from the
inside and there's the view from the
outside. On this chart, the first six
timelines present church history as it
would be explained from inside various
denominations, whereas the final
timeline presents church history from an
outside perspective in an attempt to be
as objective and neutral as possible. I
think it's important for people to
understand the difference, so that when
say they're watching a video here on
YouTube, they can distinguish between
whether they're watching a religious
video, meaning someone from a particular
religion talking about their beliefs
from an insider perspective, or a
religious studies video, meaning someone
who is talking about religion from an
outsider perspective. Okay, so let's
dive in. The first timeline shows church
history from the Catholic perspective.
From the Catholic perspective, the
church led by Rome is the one true
church, the one founded by Jesus. Other
churches, such as the Eastern Orthodox
Church led by Constantinople or the
Protestants, split from them and to this
day they remain separated from the main
body of Christians, which is the
Catholic Church led by the Pope. In
contrast, from the Orthodox perspective,
it was the Catholics who split from them
and are therefore now separated from the
one true church.
And since the Protestants split from the
Catholics, they are even more separated
from the main body of Christians, which
is the Eastern Orthodox Church. In both
cases, the Oriental Orthodox Church in
places like Egypt and Ethiopia is seen
as being a branch that split off even
earlier. Next, let's skip to the
Lutheran Reformed timeline. Here, the
idea is that the original church
eventually became corrupted during the
Middle Ages, but was then put back on
the right path by the Protestant
Reformation. So, in this view, the
mainline Protestant denominations, such
as the Anglicans, Lutherans, and
Calvinists, represent a continuation of
the one true church, whereas the Roman
Catholics and the Eastern Orthodox are
separations that continue to carry
vestiges of the medieval corruption. The
Anglican perspective is similar, but has
a softer view towards other churches.
For example, when it comes to the Great
Schism, it sees neither the Catholic
Church nor the Eastern Orthodox Church
as being the one true church, but rather
as being different branches. Just like
they, the Anglicans are yet another
branch. Then we come to the Baptist
Trail of Blood Theory, which I should
point out is not actually held by most
Baptists. Most Baptists today would more
likely adhere to something closer to the
Lutheran Reformed Theory. But this
particular theory stands out to me
because it's the one that I was taught
as a kid growing up in the Worldwide
Church of God, albeit with a small
twist. Here, the idea is that the one
true church went into hiding sometime
after the Council of Nicaea and that all
the big churches are, well, to put it
frankly, wrong. In this view, certain
Baptist churches today, while few in
number in the grand scheme of things,
are the direct descendants of the true,
sometimes hidden, church that has always
existed. Now, what I was taught as a kid
was that the Worldwide Church of God was
the continuation of that one true
church. And while I no longer believe
that, there are in fact some churches
that still do. Correct me if I'm wrong,
but I think that the Seventh-day
Adventists believe something akin to
this particular theory as well. Next up
is a view that's a little more common,
as it's the one held by Mormons,
Jehovah's Witnesses, as well as
restorationist churches, such as the
Disciples of Christ and the Churches of
Christ. Here, the idea is that the
original church fell very early on into
apostasy, meaning that they veered off
the correct path and that for centuries
there was no one true church in
existence. But then, due to the work of
either Joseph Smith, Charles Russell, or
Stone and Campbell, the church was
restored and therefore either the LDS or
Churches of Christ represent the one
true church today. So, what all of these
perspectives so far have in common is
that they are views from the inside. So,
for example, if you were to go to a
theology department in a school
associated with one of the above
churches, you might be taught something
along those lines. However, if you were
to go to a religious studies department,
what you would be taught would be
something similar to this last timeline.
And that is that basically the original
church has had a lot of splits over the
years and that no one branch is
necessarily more right than any other.
They're just different. You see, the
goal of religious studies is not to tell
you who's right and who's wrong. It's
simply to describe religion from a
historical perspective using standard
academic tools such as the historical
method, which is what I try to do on
this channel. Take for example my World
Religions Family Tree chart. It does not
represent the insider view of each
religion. If it did, Islam would start
with Adam, Jainism would start millions
of years ago, and so forth. And it would
be impossible to unite everything
together. So, instead, this chart
presents the outsider view for all
religions. Now, one last thing. Keep in
mind that a person does not need to be
an atheist in order to explain religion
in a religious studies way. Take for
example the channel Ready to Harvest.
The host of that channel, Joshua,
happens to be an independent Baptist.
But whenever he talks about other
denominations, he doesn't do so from a
Baptist perspective. Instead, he simply
takes the outsider point of view and
presents the facts only, never his own
opinion. This is in contrast to a
somewhat similar channel, the Redeemed
Zoomer, who often does present things
from his own insider point of view and
often does share his personal opinion.
Now, I'm not saying it's wrong for him
to do that. I'm just saying that as a
viewer, you should be able to recognize
the difference between the two different
ways to talk about religion. Okay, let
me know in the comments who your
favorite religion YouTubers are and
which of the two perspectives they take.
Thanks for watching.